Okay boker tov good morning we are today's דף *daf* is דף
צדי *Daf Tzadi* 90 and we pick up on עמוד ב *Amud
Bet* 89B at the two dots where it says מעשר Maaser. קודם
לעופות *Ma'aser Kodem Le'ofot*. It's about 10 lines from the bottom and
we are dealing now with the principle of, first we had the
principle that whatever comes more regularly takes precedent, now we have the
principle that whatever is holier takes precedent. Of course the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s going to get to a question, let's say you have a
competition between the regular and the holy, so we'll get to that.
But now within this question about what's holier raises of course questions
because sometimes it's not on an obvious linear scale. There are different
things to look at and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you know, the
משנה Mishna *Mishnah* sort of lists which are the salient factors to
determine this hierarchy or this precedence, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sometimes
questions why not look at some of the other features to which
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s general answer is: No, we decided this was
the more important feature.
So anyway, within that, 10 lines from the bottom, מעשר Maaser קודם
לעופות *Ma'aser Kodem Le'ofot*. So מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah *Ma'aser Behemah* comes
before birds because the presumption being that, you know, things that are
going to be animals are, you know, animals, I always say animals,
mammals are more important than birds and the reason given in the
משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* is because רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* throws in the idea
that most sacrifices are of course of the larger mammal animals but
also because those you also put the entrails on the מזבח mizbe'ach
*Mizbe'ach* whereas by the bird you only put the, you know, you
only put the blood on the מזבח mizbeach, *Mizbe'ach*. So let's take
a look. אדרבה adarabba, *Adderaba*, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, let's say
the opposite. עופות קדמי *Ofot Kadmi*, birds should come before at least
מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah *Ma'aser Behemah* because שכן קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim
*Sheken Kodshei Kodashim*, birds are either a חטאת chatas *Chatat* or עולה
olah *Olah*, which is קדש קדשים *Kodesh Kodashim*, and מעשר בהמה Maaser
Behemah. *Ma'aser Behemah* is essentially like a שלמים shlamim *Shelamim* and it's
קדשים קלים kodashim kalim *Kodshim Kalim*. אפילו הכי מין זבח zevach, עדיף
*Afillu Hachi Min Zevach Adif*. Nevertheless, the fact that it's זבח *Zevach*,
something like slaughtered, you know, as opposed to מליקה *Melikah* is more
important. Did I say that right? That the point the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* makes was דמה ואימורים *Dama Ve'imurim*? Yes, ויש בו קודש *Ve'yesh
Bo Kodesh*... yes, it says because it says, after it says מין
זבח *Min Zevach*, which רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says means that that's the
standard thing you do with קרבנות Korbanot, *Korbanot*, it says that there's
also קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim דמה ואימורים *Kodshei Kodashim Dama Ve'imurim*, you
have the אימורים emurim, *imurim* going on the מזבח *Mizbe'ach*. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: אמר רבינא Ravina בר
שילא אימורי קדשים קלים kodashim kalim שיצאו לפני זריקת דם פסולים *Amar
Ravina Bar Shila Imurei Kodshim Kalim Sheyatze'u Lifnei Zrikat Dam Psulim*. Okay,
let's say you have, you might remember this, the אימורים emurim. *imurim*
of קדשים קלים kodashim kalim *Kodshim Kalim*. קדשים קלים kodashim kalim. *Kodshim
Kalim* is not subject to the laws of מעילה me'ila *Me'ilah* because
it's fundamentally the owner's and under the owner's control. The only thing
that is subject to the laws of מעילה me'ila *Me'ilah* are the
אימורים emurim *imurim*, the part that goes on the altar after זריקת
הדם zerikat hadam, *Zrikat Hadam*. Once the אימורים emurim *imurim* are fit
for being put on the altar after זריקת הדם zerikat hadam *Zrikat
Hadam*, so only then do they reach this stage of considered being
fully קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim. *Kodshei Kodashim*. So the question is: what
is their status after the animal's been slaughtered before זריקת הדם zerikat
hadam. *Zrikat Hadam*? Are they like קדשים קלים kodashim kalim. *Kodshim Kalim*
or are they like קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim, *Kodshei Kodashim*, the אימורים
emurim *imurim*? What's one of the biggest differences between קדשים קלים kodashim
kalim. *Kodshim Kalim* and קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim, *Kodshei Kodashim*? Whether you
can take it out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit Hamikdash*.
So what happens if you take the אימורים emurim *imurim*...
they always go on the מזבח *Mizbe'ach*...
I know, but you're going to take them out and bring them
back. Do they become פסול pasul, *pasul* when they're brought out of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beit Hamikdash*? If they're still considered like
the meat and like קדשים קלים *Kodshim Kalim*, they don't become פסול
pasul *pasul* and then you've got to eventually you've got to bring
them back and put them on the altar. But until זריקת הדם
zerikat hadam. *Zrikat Hadam*, maybe their status hasn't really transformed. They're still
fundamentally קדשים קלים *Kodshim Kalim* and under the owner's control. Or do
you say once they're slaughtered and they're separated out and so on,
then even though there's no מעילה me'ila *Me'ilah*, they're enough קדשי קדשים
*Kodshei Kodashim* at this stage that taking them out of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash? *Beit Hamikdash* invalidates them.
And then if it's invalid...
then you can't put them on the מזבח *Mizbe'ach*. The קרבן korban
*Korban* is still kosher...
we can still go ahead with the זריקת *Zrikat*...
yeah, yeah, yeah...
you have to bring another one...
correct, correct. The קרבן Korban *Korban*'s still kosher. The question is whether
you can put it on the מזבח *Mizbe'ach*. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: The general rule is if it
doesn't have to do with blood, the קרבן korban *Korban* is kosher.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: so he
says שיצאו לפני זריקת דם פסולים *Sheyatze'u Lifnei Zrikat Dam Psulim*, they're
invalid. That yes, they're enough at a stage of קדשי קדשים *Kodshei
Kodashim* that bringing them out invalidates them, even if you bring them
back in. Again, the קרבן korban, *Korban* is still kosher. Okay, פסולים
*Psulim*. ותנא טונא *Ve'tana Tuna*, and our תנא tanna *Tanna* taught similarly:
מן שהוא זבח *Min Shehu Zevach*, it speaks about the reason מעשר
Maaser *Ma'aser*, which is קדשים קלים *Kodshim Kalim*, is better than עופות
*Ofot*, is because it is a זבח *Zevach*, it is slaughtered, ויש
בה קדשי קדשים דמה ואימוריה *Ve'yesh Bo Kodshei Kodashim Dama Ve'imurim*, and
it has two things of it which are קדשי קדשים *Kodshei Kodashim*,
the blood and the אימורים emurim *imurim*, whereas by the birds you
only have the blood. So what does that prove it? Because he's
going to say because it's a little bit redundant. It's going to
be a focus on the extra words of this משנה Mishna *Mishnah*.
בשלמא אימורים emurim ליתנהו בעופות *Bishlama Imurim Leitnu Be'ofot*, I understand it
has the אימורים emurim *imurim*, that you want to emphasize it has
the אימורים emurim *imurim* that go on the altar, you don't have
that by the birds. אלא דמיה איתא *Ela Damiya Isa*, blood is
with the עופות *ofot*. So why wasn't it just simpler? Why didn't
it just say it in a simpler way that,
you know, מעשר Maaser *Ma'aser* comes before birds because it has אימורים
*imurim*? Just say it has אימורים *imurim*. That's something extra that מעשר
Maaser *Ma'aser* has. Why does it have:
it's קדשי קדשים דמה ואימוריה *Kodshei Kodashim Dama Ve'imurim*? That's a little
redundant, that's a little verbose. אלא לאו קמשמע לן *Ela Lav Kamashma
Lan*, the reason it wants to say blood even though that's shared
between the birds and the מעשר Maaser *Ma'aser*, the reason it's saying
it is to underscore that the blood and the אימורים *imurim* of
the מעשר Maaser. *Ma'aser* are in the same category. אלא לאו קמשמע
לן אימורים *Ela Lav Kamashma
Lan imurim* The אימורים are the entrails are just like the blood.
מה דמו לפני זריקה אף אימורים קודם זריקה. ma damo lifnei zerika
af emurim kodem zerika. The same way the blood is already fully
to God's even before the זריקה, zerika, the same is true by
the אימורים, even though it's coming from קדשים קלים after the שחיטה
shechita and there's no מעילה Me'ila: yet, after שחיטה shechita it's just
like the blood. Okay.
וקרי להו קדשי קדשים vekari lehu kodshei kodashim and it's calling it
קדשי קדשים even at that stage before זריקה. zerika. Alright, so that
means again even though no מעילה me'ila. it is fully at this
קדשי קדשים stage. ומה דמו נפסל ביוצא uma damo nifsul beyotzei and
therefore I can infer the same way blood when you take it
out becomes invalid even before זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam אף אימורים נפסל
ביוצא af emurim nifsul beyotzei even the אימורים. Okay, it's a nice
דיוק, diyuk, I mean it doesn't prove it, but the fact that
it mentions blood with the אימורים when it was superfluous is coming
to tell you you should see by קדשים קלים the blood and
the אימורים are in the same category. So now we're going to
try, so the גמרא's Gemara not totally convinced, but whatever. Now we're
going to try to either prove or disprove this position that the
אימורים that go out before זריקת הדם zrikas hadam of קדשים קלים
become invalid. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara... says like this. נימא מסייע
ליה. neima mesayei lei. Let's try to prove it. בשר, basar, here's
a debate between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish.
בשר קדשים קלים שיצא לפני זריקת הדם, basar kodashim kalim sheyatza lifnei
zerikat hadam, let's see the meat of your שלמים shlamim is taken
out before the זריקת הדם. Do are you allowed to continue to
eat the meat? You're going to be able in a few minutes
to take it out, take it home, go to your nice apartment
in you know in in where you know in the old city,
no I was going to say somewhere else like I don't know
you know in Katamon or something I mean and go ahead and
you know and that's true though you have to get the אכילתה
בפנים לחומה achilasah bifnim lachomah so okay in the I know okay
in the old city. Anyway and you know and eat your steaks
but you went ahead and you were so eager you took it
out before the זריקת דמים. zerikat damim. Now you could actually imagine
something like this happens you know they slaughter they catch your blood
you know then it's all very busy, are you able to continue
to watch whether your blood has been thrown? Do they take a
number and report back to you? Presumably you know they get their
stuff done and you go home. So maybe you actually left with
your meat before the blood was thrown. What's the
story? לפני זריקת דמים, lifnei zerikat damim, רבי יוחנן אמר כשר, Rabbi
Yochanan amar kasher, the meat is
kosher. ריש לקיש אמר פסול, Reish Lakish amar pasul, it's invalid. רבי
יוחנן אמר כשר הואיל וסופו לצאת, Rabbi Yochanan amar kasher hov sofo
latzeit, after they throw the blood you're going to take it home
so it's still so so why should it be invalid just because
the blood hasn't been thrown?
Okay so the blood has to be thrown first.
Nobody's questioning the blood has to be thrown before you can eat
it but where do you get a concept that the meat of
שלמים shlamim can't be taken out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash.
because that's like the מתיר? matir?
No because it's fundamentally קדשים קלים. It's not something like a חטאת
chatas that starts fundamentally God's and then maybe you could say you
know you need it to be the blood to be thrown so
that the כהנים משלחן גבוה קזכו kohanim mishulchan gavoha kazchu are like
you know getting it back and they're eating it and so on.
Logically a שלמים shlamim, starts the other way, it starts fundamentally it's
all under your control.
Now let's say I מקדיש makdish this as a שלמים, Shelamim, I
can't work it now, I can't do any of that.
Okay but there's
no מעילה me'ila with the meat.
So I can't just use it for whatever. But you're not eating
it you're just taking it out of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash
There's no logic to assume that it has a status of קדשי
קדשים. I think what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says makes a lot
of sense. Where's the basis for saying you can't take the meat
out of the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash. So let's see. ריש לקיש
אמר פסול, Reish Lakish amar pasul, רבי יוחנן אמר כשר הואיל וסופו
לצאת. Rabbi Yochanan amar kasher hov sofo latzeit. ריש לקיש אמר פסול
עדיין לא הגיע זמנו לצאת. Reish Lakish amar pasul adayin lo higia
zmano latzeit. Okay alright well fine me and Michael can choose sides
on this debate. I'm not saying I don't understand the fact that
you're not yet allowed to eat it. I'm just saying I don't
know where that would lead to an idea that there's an איסור
issur to take it out of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash Conceptually
I don't see this starting as fundamentally קדשי קדשים, this starts fundamentally
as קדשים קלים. I don't see where that איסור issur comes from
but anyway that's ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish position. Okay. עד כאן לא
פליגי אלא בבשר, ad kan lo paligi ella bebasar,
now this whole debate is by the meat. There רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is prepared to say you take it out before the blood
is thrown it's okay, it's going out anyway. Okay אבל באימורים לא,
aval be'emurim lo, certainly the implication of this debate is that when
it comes to the אימורים everybody would agree that you when you
take it out it becomes invalid if you take it out before
זריקת הדם. There I would agree too. So there you go. And
therefore that is a proof that implicit in the debate of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is that they both
agree to רבינא's Ravina, point which is that if אימורים go out
beforehand it's invalid. So the גמרא Gemara says no not necessarily. הוא
הדין דבאימורים נמי פליגי, hu hadin de'be'emurim nami paligi, I could tell
you that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say even if you took
the אימורים out beforehand they don't become invalid. Okay והא דקמיפלגי בבשר
ve'ha dekampaligi bebasar why are they debating the meat? להודיע כוחו דריש
לקיש lehodia kocho de'Reish Lakish to tell you that even the meat
which is at the end going to come out דאפילו סופו סופו
לצאת אמר עדיין לא הגיע זמנו לצאת. dafilu sofo sofo latzeit amar
adayin lo higia zmano latzeit. And ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says even
the meat that I know is going out I will say becomes
invalid. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would prepare to say even the
אימורים would not be invalidated. It doesn't sound like it because רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan I mean you'd have to say רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan like לדבריו דריש לקיש קאמר lidvarav de'Reish Lakish qamar because when
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan explains his reason he says because the meat's
eventually going out. And now we're saying it's really not based on
that. Really for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan since the blood hasn't been
thrown even the אימורים could actually go out. Okay anyway that's it.
So the simple sense of that debate is they both agree with
רבינא, Ravina. but the גמרא Gemara pushes back. לימא כתנאי, Leima k'tanna'ei,
let's say this question about the אימורין eimurin going out before the
blood is a debate of תנאים. tanna'im. What's the because we have
the following from מעילה: me'ila. אימורי קדשים קלים שיצאו לפני זריקת דמם.
Eimurei kodashim kalim she-yatz'u lifnei zrikas damam. Here you go. Looks like
exactly going to be our case. אימורין eimurin that went out before
the blood was thrown. רבי אליעזר אומר אין מועלין בהן, Rabbi Eliezer
omer ein mo'alin bahen, there's no מעילה. me'ila. That everybody agrees. Well,
actually no. Meaning אין מועלין בהן ein mo'alin bahen even after the
blood is thrown. Okay, everybody agrees there's no מעילה me'ila. until the
blood is thrown. But you took it out, and then you threw
the blood. So now that you threw the blood, there should be
מעילה. me'ila,
But if the אימורין eimurin became פסול, pasul there's no מעילה. me'ila,
Okay, so by saying אין מועלין בהן, ein mo'alin bahen, he's implicitly
saying you've invalidated the אימורין eimurin and therefore even after you throw
the blood, there won't be any מעילה. me'ila, Okay, so אין מועלין
בהן ein mo'alin bahen ואין חייבין ve-ein chayavin top of דף צ'
daf tzadi ואין חייבין עליהן משום פיגול נותר וטמא. ve-ein chayavin aleihen
mishum pigul nosar ve-tamei. You don't transgress any of these things. Since
it's already פסול pasul. with יוצא, yotzei, so now if you went
ahead and before when you got around to throwing the blood, you
were thinking I'm going to throw the blood now to offer up
the אימורין eimurin tomorrow, you don't make it פיגול pigul because the
אימורין eimurin are already invalid. So a thought to do the wrong
time with the אימורין eimurin doesn't make it doesn't make it פיגול
pigul because it's already invalid. Similarly, if you leave over the אימורין
eimurin you're not חייב chayav for נותר nosar because it's it's invalid
and you're not חייב chayav if you're טמא tamei and eat the
אימורין eimurin even though nobody's supposed to be eating the אימורין, eimurin,
but there is a חיוב כרת chiyuv kares for טמא tamei person
to eat either the meat of a קרבן Korban or the אימורין,
eimurin, but it would only apply to כשר kosher אימורין, eimurin, not
פסול pasul אימורין. eimurin. So all of this is a long way
of saying that taking it out before the זריקת הדם invalidates, which
seems to be exactly the position of רבינא. Ravina. רבי עקיבא אומר
מועלין בהן וחייבין עליהן משום פיגול נותר וטמא. Rabbi Akiva omer mo'alin
bahen ve-chayavin aleihen mishum pigul nosar ve-tamei. Nope, all of these things
still apply, you did not invalidate it. So there you go, it's
a debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
What more do you want? גמרא Gemara, asks, why just go to
that? Well, we'll you'll see in a minute. מאי לאו דהדר עיילינהו?
Mai lav de-hadar ayileinhu? Are they not talking about the fact that
you took the אימורין eimurin out and you brought them back in?
And there and even there רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says once you
brought them out once, once you brought them out, boom, they're invalid.
So the גמרא Gemara says
ומר סבר דמר סבר מיפסלי ביוצא ומר סבר לא מיפסלי ביוצא. u-mar
savar de-mar savar mipsali be-yotzei u-mar savar lo mipsali be-yotzei. One says
they become invalid when they're brought out and the other says they
don't. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, no. דהדר עיילינהו כולי עלמא
לא פליגי. De-hadar ayileinhu kuli alma lo pligi. No, you don't have
to say that that is a debate and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
sides with רבינא. Ravina. Actually, everybody could reject רבינא. Ravina. Everybody could
say when you bring it out, it does not become פסול. pasul?
And if you bring it back in before the blood is thrown,
totally fine. And it's כשר kosher and you can put it on
the מזבח and there is מעילה, me'ilah, פיגול, pigul, נותר, nosar, and
טמא tamei that if you act the act of bringing it out
did not invalidate it, and as long as you brought it back
before the זריקת הדם you're safe. You could say that's the point.
What's their debate then?
כי פליגי והכא בדאיתנהו אבראי פליגי. Ki pligi ve-hacha be-de-isneihu abarai pligi.
The debate is that the אימורין eimurin are still out from the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, when the blood is being thrown. Oh, okay,
if they're out when the blood is being thrown, then you want
to know that everybody should say it becomes פסול pasul, because now
the blood is thrown and now it's outside the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash, Okay, ובהא פליגי. u-ve-ha pligi. So here's the debate. So then
what's the position of of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that says it
doesn't become פסול? pasul It's outside of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash,
when the blood is being thrown. דמר סבר אין זריקה מועלת ליוצא
ומר סבר זריקה מועלת ליוצא. De-mar savar ein zrika mo'ales le-yotzei u-mar
savar zrika mo'ales le-yotzei. The point is because it's out of the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash? the blood when it's thrown might not be
relevant to it. It might be that since it's not where in
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash on the one hand it's not פסול,
pasul and if you bring it back, no harm no foul, you
know, get it back in time nobody will pretend it didn't happen.
Okay, but if it's outside when the blood is being thrown, the
throwing of the blood is not relevant to it. It's like it
doesn't exist vis-a-vis the blood being thrown. Not that it's פסול pasul.
but doesn't exist. And if it doesn't exist, then the throwing of
the blood didn't change its state. So if the throwing of the
blood didn't change its state, it never got to the higher level
of being the transgression of מעילה, פיגול, pigul, נותר, nosar, טמא, tamei,
etc. Right, פיגול, pigul, a thought of פיגול pigul isn't relevant to
it. It's like it doesn't exist if it's out of the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash which explains why by the way this seems like
דחוק, d'chuk, but actually no. Why didn't they just debate whether it
becomes פסול pasul. or not? Why did they go immediately to the
question of מעילה, פיגול, pigul, נותר, nosar, and טמא? tamei? So this
actually makes sense because nobody is saying it became פסול. pasul. They're
not agreeing with רבינא. Ravina It did not become פסול. pasul. What
we want to know is does the throwing of the blood raise
its state when it's out of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash Okay,
and that's the debate. Whether the blood of the throwing of the
blood is relevant to it, not whether it became פסול. Alright, that's
a nice explanation. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, והא
ve-ha one minute, so that's how רב פפא Rav Pappa explains this
debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva which
is fine, which means that everybody rejects רבינא Ravina, according to this.
So we've said our תנא implicitly agrees with רבינא, Ravina. now we're
saying this debate of תנאים tanna'im everybody rejects רבינא. Ravina But one
minute, there's a similar debate of רבי רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva by what happens if the bread is of
a תודה, Todah, excuse me, the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem of the,
of the קרבן Korban for שבועות Shavuot is outside of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash, when you're throwing the blood. And it's the same
debate whether, you know, it changes the status of the שתי הלחם
Shtei Halechem or not. And the same רב פפא Rav Pappa here
who said that they're debating when it's outside at the time of
the throwing of the blood said the opposite over there. רמינהו, Reminehu,
let's read it.
רמינהו לגופיה שתי
הלחם דקדשי במדבח.
Reminehu legufei
Shtei Halechem dekadshi bemidbach.
I understand, but what does the גמרא Gemara, say? והא רב פפא
הוא דאמר בדאיתנהו לבראי כולי עלמא לא פליגי בדאיילינהו לגואי פליגי. Veha
Rav Pappa hu de'amar bede'isnehu livrai kuli alma lo pligi bede'aylinehu legavai
pligi.
When it comes to the שתי הלחם, Shtei Halechem, he says the
flip, the same רב פפא. Rav Pappa. He says that רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva both agree that if your
שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem are out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash,
when the blood is thrown, the blood is not relevant to them,
and what they're debating is when it was taken out and brought
back in. So the גמרא Gemara says הני מילי גבי שתי הלחם
דלאו גופיה דזבחא. Hani milei gabei Shtei Halechem delav gufei dezivcha. Right,
as Michael said, the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem is something a completely
different thing than the actual animal itself. So there, because it's physically,
it's a separate thing, it's bread, you know, it's not the part
of the animal, everybody would agree if it's out of the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash when the blood is being thrown, the blood does
not connect to it. It's bizarre enough that the throwing of the
blood connects to something that's not the animal itself. So if you
want that throwing of the blood to connect to it, everybody would
agree there that it has to be in the בית המקדש, and
if you did it and if it was outside, the throwing of
the blood did not raise its status. Okay, and they're debating inside
for what?
Anyone can eat it, like a זר zar or anyone?
No, no, no, it's still been sanctified, there's still, you know, but
it doesn't have the, you know, it doesn't have these various violations:
פיגול, pigul, נותר, nosar, טמא, tamei, these types of things and so
on. So what happens to it? I mean, I suppose you would
have to burn it, you know, burn it, I guess. I don't
know, wait for עיבור צורה ibur tzura probably and burn it. I
don't know, it's a good question. Okay, so there the debate is
about what do you call it? Is about,
nu, is about what, there they are debating whether the blood affects
it once you've brought it back in. But there it's something that
has a weaker connection. So there you need it, everybody agrees if
it's outside, the blood isn't connected to it. אבל אימורין דגופיה דזבחא
הוא, Aval imurin degufei dezivcha hu, but the אימורין imurin that come
from the animal itself, בדאיתנהו לבראי פליגי. bede'isnehu livrai pligi. There רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, there רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say even if
the אימורין imurin are outside of the בית המקדש, the blood is
relevant to it and changes and raises its status. Okay, but again,
everybody might say that bringing it out does not per se invalidate
it. The question is whether if it's outside, is the throwing of
the blood relevant to it. So we don't have, if any, and
as I said, it's interesting, neither of them say פסול. They speak
about מעילה, פיגול, pigul, נותר, nosar, טמא. tamei. So according to this
read, both רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva reject
רבינא's position. But we don't know. We don't know. Now we're moving
on. Okay, yet again something that remains unresolved. Okay, so עופות קודמין,
Ofos kodmin, birds come before מנחה mincha because birds have blood and
מנחות minchos don't, and that's understood to be more significant. The גמרא
Gemara says אדרבה, Adaraba, let me say the opposite, מנחות קודמין menachos
kodmin שכן ישנן בציבור כביחיד. sheken yeshnan betzibur kiveyachid. You can bring
a מנחת ציבור minchas tzibur like the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem like
we just mentioned, okay, and the עומר. Omer. So the גמרא... gemara
that gives it more weight. So the גמרא gemara says אפילו הכי
מיני דמים עדיפי. afillu hachi minei damim adifei. No, something with blood
is still considered more important, that's more powerful, it atones and so
on. Again, this is all making choices. Okay, I guess that's life,
making choices, you know. But the point is it's not clearly all
on some linear scale. All right, מנחת חוטא. Minchas Chotei. Now, a
מנחה mincha of a, for a sin, which is for example like
you know you have some things which are עולה ויורד oleh veyored
which, you know, variable, like טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumath mikdash vekodashav or
these types of things where if you don't have the money you
can bring a מנחה mincha instead of bringing like a, you can
either bring like a mammal and if you don't have the money
you bring a bird and if you don't have the bird then
you can go ahead and bring a מנחה. mincha. So sometimes the
מנחה mincha is brought to as a substitute for a חטאת chatas
in a small number of cases. Okay, and if so, that comes
before a standard מנחה mincha the same way a
חטאת chatas comes before an עולה olah because to be מכפר mechaper
for sin is considered more significant. Okay, so let's take a look.
By the way, I should say that it is fascinating this idea,
I wasn't here yesterday, so let me just mention it, that a
מנחה mincha comes before an עולה olah, because atoning for sin is
more important, even though the limbs of an עולה, olah, you know,
come before the אימורין imurin of a חטאת chatas because obviously one
is fully burned. So if you had to ask yourself, you know,
which קרבן Korban do you think is like the paradigmatic קרבן, Korban,
right, I think many of us would sort of speak about the
עולה, olah? right, because in general if you talk look at the
תורה, Torah, right, we've mentioned this before, whereas the הלכה halakha here
totally focuses on the blood and sees everything else as secondary, if
you read the stories in the תורה, Torah, it's all about that
you were מעלה, ma'aleh, you offered it up and you burnt it
on the altar and the smoke went up and so on, you
know. So the emphasis of burning something seems to be primary.
Like where did it say that a מנחה mincha comes before an
עולה? olah? You said מנחה mincha comes before an עולה? olah.
No, I said a מנחת חטאת minchas chatas comes before a standard,
a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei comes before a normal מנחה mincha the
same way a חטאת Chatat comes before an עולה. Olah. Right. Okay.
So anyway, but if you had, I'm going back to... the חטאת
Chatat coming before the עולה. Olah If you had to choose between
those, I think intuitively we would have said an עולה Olah comes
first. An עולה's Olah. fully burnt, that's like your paradigmatic קרבן Korban
and so on. And not only that, if you read ויקרא, Vayikra,
the first קרבן korban is אם עולה קרבנו מן הבקר, im Olah
korbano min habakar, right? So it's the first קרבן korban, it speaks
about is an עולה. Olah. And the עולת תמיד, Olat Tamid, the
thing you bring every day is an עולה. Olah So logically we
would have thought that an עולה Olah. comes first. Okay, so the
גמרא gemara should concede the point when you're getting around to the
burning, but nevertheless with this focus on the מכפר, mechaper, on the
blood, and the blood is about
כפרה, kapara, כי ואני נתתיו לכם על המזבח לכפר על נפשותיכם, ki
va'ani netativ lachem al hamizbeach lechaper al nafshoteichem, etc., it has the
blood of a חטאת Chatat coming before the blood of an עולה.
Olah. You know actually when you get to the whole question about
why the, you know, what is the purpose of קרבנות, Korbanot, right?
רמב"ן Ramban sort of sees that when he describes the purpose of
קרבנות, korbanot. he focuses on the חטאת Chatat, and he speaks about
when you sin, you know, it's sort of like you, you know,
like you've lost the right to your own life, you know, you
owe your life to God, you deserve to die, you're going to
bring a חטאת, Chatat sort of it'll be sort of vicarious what's
done to the חטאת Chatat is like it's done to you, you
experience what you're deserving, you know, death etc., very, very sin oriented.
You know, I would have said if I was sort of describing
it, I would have focused on the עולה. Olah. It's not about
deserving to die. If you think about the first קרבן, korban who
brings the first קרבן korban in the
תורה? Torah? קין והבל, Kayin veHevel, and what you're doing is you're
bringing of some of the wealth that God has given to you,
some of the bounty God has given to you, you're offering it
to God, right? That's like an עולה. Olah You're giving it as
a gift to God, you're putting it all on the altar, you're
giving it back to God. And to the degree we're talking about
something about a life force, you could say that it's symbolic of
the fact that you want to give yourself to God, not because
you deserve to die, not about a sin, but it's a desire
to, you know, give yourself fully over to God, so instead you
give over something that represents a life but that isn't, you know,
a human life. Anyway, so I think that whole question of whether
you focus on the עולה Olah, and you focus on the חטאת
Chatat is a fascinating one, and it does get to this hyperfocus
on the blood. Anyway, so once we've established that, that a חטאת
Chatat comes before an עולה, Olah, we're going to say similar that
a מנחת חוטא Minchat Chotei comes before a standard מנחה. Mincha. Okay,
so let's take a look.
Which of the neighbors was the one accepted, a מנחה Mincha offering
or an animal?
Well, it was the animal one, which is always sort of funny
because, you know, קין Kayin was the one to initiate, right? So
anyway, that's a whole fascinating issue, let's not digress. Okay. אדרבה, says
the גמרא, gemara מנחת נדבה קודמת שכן טעונה שמן ולבונה. Minchat Nedava
kodemet shekein teuna shemen ulevona. There are things that make it look
that a מנחת נדבה Minchat Nedava is more weighty and significant. You
have the oil, you have the frankincense. מנחת חוטא Minchat Chotei is
very plain. אפילו הכי מנחת חוטא הבאה על חטא עדיפא דמכפרת. Afilu
hachi Minchat Chotei haba'ah al cheit adifa dimechaperet. And here's again the
point similar to חטאת chatas and עולה, olah. but here it's even
more heightened that point that even though it's very plain and seems
to be of a very low level, the fact that it achieves
atonement gives it greater weight.
So what about a סוטה Sota then?
Exactly next question: איבעיא להו מנחת סוטה ומנחת נדבה איזה מהן קודמת.
Iba'ya lehu Minchat Sota uMinchat Nedava eizeh mehen kodemet. How about if
it's a מנחה Mincha for a סוטה? Sota? סוטה, Sota, which is
not about atoning for sin, it's about the issue of a potential
sin but it's not about atoning for sin. מנחת נדבה קודמת שכן
טעונה שמן ולבונה. Minchat Nedava kodemet shekein teuna shemen ulevona. Do we
say מנחת נדבה Minchat Nedava is nicer? It's got oil, it's got
the frankincense, it's clearly of a weightier of a status, right? או
דלמא מנחת סוטה קדמה שכן באה לברר עוון? O dilma Minchat Sota
kadma shekein ba'ah levarer avon? It might not be atoning, but it's
doing something more essential. Okay, so there's
no atonement but still, you know, you can say to make שלום
shalom between a husband and his wife, to determine sin, that's at
least a more essential function than just סתם stam the giving of
a מנחה. Mincha. תא שמע: Ta shema: מנחת חוטא קודמת למנחת נדבה.
Minchat Chotei kodemet leMinchat Nedava. Our משנה Mishnah. says a מנחה Mincha
for sin comes before. מנחת חוטא הוא דקדמה למנחת נדבה. Minchat Chotei
hu dekadma leMinchat Nedava. It's only a מנחה Mincha that's about atoning
for sin. הא מנחת סוטה לא. Ha Minchat Sota lo. Presumably a
מנחת סוטה, Minchat Sota, which is not called a מנחת חוטא. Minchat
Chotei. I mean, it's funny, the תורה Torah actually calls it כי
מנחת קנאת היא. ki Minchat Kena'ot hi. It does, but it doesn't
call it מנחת חוטא. Minchat Chotei. Okay, so therefore presumably a מנחה
Mincha of a סוטה Sota does not come first. Says no: מי
קתני משום דהיא מכפרת? Mi katani mishum dehi mechaperet? Look at the
reason given in the משנה. Mishnah. It doesn't say a מנחת חוטא
Minchat Chotei comes first because it atones. משום דבאה על חטא קתני.
Mishum deba'ah al cheit katani. It actually, the terminology used is subtly
different. It doesn't say it atones for sin; it says it's coming
because of sin. Well, guess what? That description actually aptly fits a
סוטה Sota as
well. והא נמי באה על חטא. Veha nami ba'ah al cheit. So
actually if anything you can infer from the language of our משנה
mishna that a מנחת סוטה Minchat Sota does come before a standard
מנחה. Mincha. תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here.
But not before a מנחת חוטא, Minchat Chotei, though, right?
Right. זו קודמת לזו. Zu kodemet lezu. We've got a ברייתא: Baraita:
this comes before this. שזו באה מן החטים וזו באה מן השעורים.
Shezu ba'ah min hachitim vezu ba'ah min hase'orim. So that the one
comes from wheat and the one comes from barley. Now, which are
we talking about? That's a difference between מנחת חוטא Minchat Chotei and
מנחת נדבה. Minchat Nedava. It's also a difference between מנחת סוטה Minchat
Sota and מנחת נדבה. Minchat Nedava. So which one are we comparing?
מאי לאו מנחת נדבה למנחת סוטה. Mai lau Minchat Nedava leMinchat Sota.
Presumably. Presumably the emphasis of wheat versus barley was comparing a מנחת
נדבה minchas nedava to a מנחת סוטה minchas sotah and therefore it's
telling you that a מנחת נדבה minchas nedava comes first. This is
wheat, this is barley. One is a nicer one, the other is
a less nicer one. So there's your answer. And that would say
that a מנחת סוטה minchas sotah would come
second. לא מנחת חוטא למנחת סוטה. Lo minchas chotei l'minchas sotah. No,
actually it's talking about a מנחת חוטא. minchas chotei. A מנחת חוטא
minchas chotei actually I just misstated a second ago. I'm sorry. A
מנחת חוטא minchas chotei actually also comes from wheat. The only one
that comes from barley is the מנחת סוטה, minchas sotah, right? מאכל
בהמה, ma'achal behema, the famous רש"י, Rashi or the עומר. omer. Correct.
Okay. So, so correct. So therefore what this will tell you is
a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei comes before a מנחת סוטה, minchas sotah,
but maybe סוטה sotah comes before נדבה? nedava? So the גמרא gemara
says one minute. תיפוק ליה דהא מכפר והא לא מכפר, Teipok lei
deha michaper v'ha lo michaper, as Michael himself intuited, it's obvious the
מנחת חוטא minchas chotei comes before because our question is what weight
does a מנחת סוטה minchas sotah have. Clearly though the מנחת חוטא
minchas chotei is the weightiest because it achieves atonement. So if you
were trying to say a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei before a סוטה,
sotah, why emphasize wheat versus barley? Emphasize atone versus not atone. So
the גמרא Gemara says ואלא מאי? v'ela mai? So what do you
want to say the ברייתא braisa is comparing? מנחת נדבה, Minchas nedava,
you want to say that it's comparing a normal מנחה mincha to
a סוטה sotah and says a normal מנחה mincha is better because
it's wheat versus barley. If that were true, why go to the
wheat and barley? תיפוק ליה דזו טעונה שמן ולבונה וזו אינה טעונה
שמן ולבונה. Teipok lei dezu teuna shemen ulevona v'zu einah teuna shemen
ulevona. There's another thing you could have pointed to, the oil and
the frankincense. So wherever you want to say clearly we're in agreement
that the barley thing is being referred to as the סוטה. sotah.
But the question is which is it being ranked below? Is it
being ranked below the מנחת חוטא minchas chotei or is it being
ranked below the מנחת נדבה? minchas nedava? And either one, says the
גמרא, Gemara there's more to say than just the wheat versus barley.
You could have spoken about atoning versus not atone, about oil and
frankincense versus not. אלא חד מתרי טעמי נקט. Ela chad mitrei ta'amei
nakat. You're right. It could have said a few different things. It's
so clearly there's other things to say, so we can't prove which
one is it being ranked below. Don't tell me oh it's not
being ranked below this because then it would have said something else.
No, there's always more explanations to rank this below either one of
them. Okay, so it's not clear. We have a מנחת סוטה minchas
sotah being ranked below a certain מנחה, mincha, and this is exactly
our question. Is it ranked below a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei but
it still comes before מנחת נדבה minchas nedava because it's coming to
determine sin and it's about sin and so on? Or is it
even ranked below a מנחת נדבה minchas nedava and that we don't
know? So at the end of the day we don't know the
answer where a מנחת סוטה minchas sotah appears on the hierarchy. Okay,
yes. He's got a lot of non-resolved issues. Okay. חטאת העוף קודמת.
Chatas ha'of kodemas. Now, a bird חטאת chatas comes before a bird
עולה. olah. Same type of an idea. Right, that's the
משנה. חטאת העוף קודמת לעולת העוף. Chatas ha'of kodemas l'olas ha'of. Right,
so once again a חטאת chatas comes before an עולה. olah Okay,
by the way, by a מנחה mincha it wasn't exactly a direct
comparison to an עולה olah because a מנחה mincha is eaten. Okay,
but it still is a חטאת chatas coming before whatever. That's I
guess less of a חידוש, chiddush, okay, since you're going to eat
the rest of the מנחה. mincha. Okay, but here anyway we're back
to the חטאת chatas versus עולה olah. comparison. Okay, so a bird
חטאת chatas comes before a bird עולה. olah
מנא הני מילי? Minani mili? Where do you know this from? דתנו
רבנן Detanu rabbanan that we taught: והקריב את אשר לחטאת ראשונה. v'hikriv
es asher l'chatas rishona. Okay, this is, you know, this is going
talking about by a when it's brought these two things are brought
for a חטאת chatas. and a bird עולה olah. are brought for
a sin. This is like I said a קרבן עולה
ויורד. korban
oleh v'yored.
Says at the end of פרשת ויקרא Parshas Vayikra 5:8.
Exactly. Thank you. 5:8 you said? Yeah, there you
go. No, not 5:8. Oh, yes it is. I was at four.
I was on four, you were right. Okay. So it says here
the sins that you could bring an עולה ויורד oleh v'yored for:
שמע קול אלה או עד או ראה או ידע ולא יגיד, Shama
kol ala o eid o ra'ah o yada v'lo yagid, so somebody
שבועת עדות shevuas eidus or טומאה, tumah, okay, or שבועה. shevua. והיה
כי יאשם לאחת מאלה
והביא את אשמו לה' על חטאתו אשר חטא נקבה מן הצאן v'haya
ki yesham l'achas me'eileh v'heivi es ashamo l'Hashem al chataso asher chata
nekeiva min hatzon etc. You bring a חטאת. chatas, And then it
says in
5:7: ואם לא תגיע ידו די שה והביא את אשמו אשר חטא
שתי תורים או שני בני יונה, v'im lo tagia yado dei seh
v'heivi es ashamo asher chata shtei sorim o shnei bnei yona, two
birds, אחד לחטאת ואחד לעולה. echad l'chatas v'echad l'olah. Okay. And then
afterwards if you can't afford that then you bring a מנחה. mincha.
So the מנחת חוטא minchas chotei we were talking about was also
in that list. But in the middle of that list of the
variable cost חטאת, chatas you have the two birds. And within the
two birds it says: והביאם אל הכהן והקריב את אשר לחטאת ראשונה.
v'hiviam el hakohen v'hikriv es asher l'chatas rishona. Oh my God! Actually
it's explicit in the verse! It's not even a דיוק! deiyuk! והקריב
את אשר לחטאת ראשונה. v'hikriv es asher l'chatas rishona. Bring the חטאת
chatas bird first. Okay. And then it speaks about ואת השני יעשה
עולה כמשפט. v'es hasheini ya'aseh ola kamishpat. And the second one you
do an עולה. olah So at least for the bird חטאת chatat
versus עולה olah comparison. by the חטאת chatat and עולה olah. bird,
it is explicit that the חטאת chatat comes before the עולה. olah.
Okay? Which by the way I should just say is not necessarily
the same as the question about ראובן Reuven brought a חטאת chatat
and שמעון Shimon brought an עולה. olah Okay? When one person is
bringing a חטאת עולה Chattas Olah package, you know, the way it's
usually explained is, first you bring the חטאת chatat to atone and
then you can give the gift to God, the עולה, olah, but
while, you know, when you're still on the outs with God as
it were, the עולה olah is not the appropriate thing to bring,
right? So first you have to say you're sorry before you can
then bring the עולה. olah. So the fact that within that case
where an atonement is needed, and the חטאת עולה Chattas Olah comes
as a package, a חטאת chatat comes first is not necessarily logically
the same as saying if you got ראובן Reuven here who's a
sinner and he's bringing a חטאת chatat and שמעון Shimon who's just
bringing an עולה olah that you should go to ראובן Reuven first.
Right? That's like a different question, but the גמרא Gemara, assumes the
same. Okay. מנא הני מילי? Mina hani milei? How do you know
that a bird חטאת chatat comes before a bird עולה? olah דתנו
רבנן, Detanu rabanan, our rabbis taught: והקריב את אשר לחטאת ראשונה. Vehikriv
et asher lachatat rishona. מה תלמוד לומר? Ma talmud lomar? What is
it teaching you? שאין תלמוד לומר She’ein talmud lomar ללמד שתקרב ראשונה.
lilmed shetikarev rishona. Okay, it's not teaching you that it just is
brought first. That's like, you know, why not? It is saying that.
הרי כבר נאמר Harei kevar ne’emar because the next verse says ואת
השני יעשה עולה כמשפט. Ve’et hasheni ya’aseh olah kamishpat. It says that
the עולה olah? comes second. אלא זה בני אב. Ela zeh binyan
av. So why is it saying the חטאת chatat comes first if
it's already implicitly going to say it comes first by saying that
the עולה olah comes second? Because this is to teach you a
general rule לכל חטאות שיקרבו לעולות הבאות עמהם. lechol chata’ot sheyikrevu le’olot
haba’ot imahem. A
חטאת chatat always comes before an עולה. olah Now what's the always?
So partly you could say what I just said, even if it's
choosing between two different people's קרבנות. But the גמרא Gemara also says
it in the following way: בין חטאת העוף לעולת העוף, bein chatat
ha’of le’olat ha’of, whether it's the case we're dealing with, a bird
חטאת chatat before a bird
עולה, olah. בין חטאת בהמה לעולת בהמה, bein chatat behemah le’olat behemah,
a mammal חטאת chatat before a mammal עולה, olah, ואפילו, va’afilu, here's
the חידוש, chiddush, okay, if that's why there was an extra פסוק
pasuk here to tell you always, always means ואפילו חטאת העוף לעולת
בהמה. afilu chatat ha’of le’olat behemah. If you had to choose ראובן
Reuven brought his sin offering, the חטאת העוף, chatat ha’of, or a
woman brought it let's say for טומאה tumah purposes, by the way
that's important to note, not all חטאות chata’ot come for sin, the
emphasis of כפרה, kaparah, a lot of חטאות chata’ot come actually for
cleansing and for טהרה taharah purposes, and we're not distinguishing between them.
So even a classic case of a bird חטאת chatat would be
a woman bringing it after childbirth. Okay, so anyway you've got a
bird חטאת chatat and a sheep or a cow that's an עולה,
olah, the bird comes before the cow. That's a big
חידוש. chiddush. Okay. הלכך, Hilkach, and there now here's how we learn
all these things out. חטאת העוף לעולת העוף Chatat ha’of le’olat ha’of
מואת השני. me’ve’et hasheni. The fact that a חטאת העוף chatat ha’of
comes first is our what we just read because it says the
second one is an עולה, olah, which implies the first one is
a חטאת. chatat
חטאת בהמה לעולת בהמה, Chatat behemah le’olat behemah, the fact that a
חטאת chatat. of a sheep or a cow comes first to an
עולה, olah, מדרבי רחמנא, miderabbi rachmana, since the Torah you know what
we learned at the end of yesterday, ופר שני בן בקר תקח
לחטאת. upar sheni ben bakar tikach lachatat. Okay, we had a פסוק
pasuk yesterday about the larger animals that the חטאת chatat comes first.
And חטאת העוף לעולת בהמה, chatat ha’of le’olat behemah, how do you
know even a bird חטאת chatat comes before an עולה olah, that's
a cow? So מזה בני אב. mizeh binyan av. That's because the
פסוק pasuk had an extra verse here by the birds and it
said, you know, and the פסוק pasuk said והקריב את אשר לחטאת
ראשונה vehikriv et asher lachatat rishona to tell you a חטאת chatat
always comes first, even a bird חטאת chatat comes first. Okay. תא
שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. Now we're going to check this.
Is this really true that a bird חטאת chatat comes before a
cow עולה? olah That seems going a little far. So we're going
to actually see if this is true. תא שמע, Ta shema, come
and hear. רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: כל מקום שנתחלפה חטאת
חטאת קודמת. kol makom shenitchalfah chatat chatat kodemet. Wherever a חטאת chatat
was exchanged, a חטאת chatat comes first. וכאן
ביולדת
עולה קודמת.
vekhan beyoledet
olah kodemet. Now what does this mean? Okay, if an עולה, olah?
if a woman is rich, I was giving the example of a
יולדת, yoledet, okay, if a woman is rich, a יולדת, yoledet, she
brings, it says
an
עולת בהמה olat behemah and a חטאת העוף. chatat ha’of. That's a
woman who is rich, okay, a rich, okay. So this is, that's
a case of יולדת עשירה. yoledet ashirah. Okay. And if she's יולדת
ענייה, yoledet aniyah,
she brings an
עולת העוף olat ha’of and a חטאת העוף, chatat ha’of, okay.
So that
changes and that stays the same. All right, you got it? So
we are saying that the חטאת העוף chatat ha’of always comes before
the עולת בהמה. olat behemah. So that would mean besides if it's
two different people, this is actually the... Perfect scenario where one person
is bringing both a bird
חטאת chatat and a large animal as an עולה. olah, This woman
who just gave birth and she's got the money for it, so
she would bring according to what we've just said, she would bring
the חטאת chatas first and the עולה olah. second. Okay, and then
certainly if she's poor, she would bring the חטאת chatas first and
the עולה olah second. That's based on what we just said, okay,
that the חטאת chatas would come first in this case. Okay, but
now we're going to see what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says and
what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says and whether that fits with the
assumption we just made, okay? So, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר, omer,
כל מקום שנתחלפה חטאת חטאת קודמת. kol makom shenitchalfa chatas chatas kodemes.
Okay,
everywhere that the תורה Torah exchanged a חטאת chatas for something, okay,
let me just check רש"י here.
Right, everywhere you started off where the חטאת chatas gets replaced and
the חטאת chatas comes first. So, if you take a look at
this case, but you take a look at a different case, right,
if you take a look at the case we just had about
like a קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh ve-yored, okay.
So what does the תורה Torah say? The תורה Torah says you
bring a if you're wealthy you bring a חטאת בהמה chatas behema
and if you're not wealthy it says you bring a חטאת העוף
chatas ha-of and an עולת העוף, olas ha-of, right? And if you
can't bring that then you bring a מנחה, mincha, okay. This is
the case of עולה ויורד. oleh ve-yored. This actually is where we
learn that you do the חטאת chatas first, where it speaks about
the עולה ויורד, oleh ve-yored, it says you bring the חטאת chatas
and then you bring the עולה. olah So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says, when it's the חטאת chatas that got exchanged, went from a
חטאת בהמה chatas behema to a חטאת העוף, chatas ha-of, and then
an עולת העוף olas ha-of got thrown in, you're going to bring
the חטאת chatas first, because here there was only, only a חטאת,
chatas so here you're going to bring the חטאת chatas, first. That's
that
case. כל מקום שנתחלפה חטאת חטאת קודמת. kol makom shenitchalfa chatas chatas
kodemes. וכאן, ve-kan, here by the יולדת, yoledes, עולה קודמת. olah kodemes.
Okay, so the עולה olah. comes first, okay, because here, okay, since
he's assuming that by the עולת בהמה olas behema and the חטאת
העוף, chatas ha-of, the עולה olah is going to come first, not
like we said, he's assuming not this way. He's assuming that the
עולה olah is going to come first. So the same way when
there was a עולת בהמה olas behema and a חטאת העוף, chatas
ha-of, he's taking it for granted that since this is a בהמה,
behema, this is larger, so this is a more significant one, this
is going to come first, he rejects the assumption we just made.
So therefore when it gets switched to an עולת העוף, olas ha-of,
this is also going to come first. You with me? So as
opposed to what we said that a bird חטאת chatas always comes
first, he says uh-uh. If you've got a cow or a sheep
that's an עולה, olah that comes first. And when you switch from
a rich יולדת yoledes to a poor יולדת, yoledes, then her bird
עולה olah, is even going to come first because when she was
rich, the sheep עולה olah came first. Okay, וכאן עולה
קודמת. ve-kan olah kodemes. כל מקום שבא על חטא kol makom she-ba
al cheit and now he's going to say the same type of
thing, חטא קודמת. cheit kodemes. וכאן עולה קודמת. ve-kan olah kodemes. And
whenever it's coming about
sin, okay, so right here where it's coming about sin, so the
חטאת chatas comes first. Here where it's not coming about sin, fundamentally
a יולדת yoledes is bringing it for a טהרה taharah process, so
if it's about sin you got to bring the חטאת chatas first.
If it's about like this sounds like a טהרה taharah process, then
the עולה olah is going to come first. Okay, חטא קודמת. cheit
kodemes. וכאן עולה קודמת. ve-kan olah kodemes. כל מקום ששניהם באים תחת
חטאת חטאת קודמת. kol makom she-shneihem ba'im tachas chatas chatas kodemes. Three
ways of explaining the difference. And here where two, the חטאת chatas
and the עולה, olah are both in exchange for the חטאת, chatas
then the חטאת chatas, is going to come first. וכאן עולה קודמת.
ve-kan olah kodemes. Here the עולה olah, comes first. So he says
there's three reasons why the order reverses between the קרבן עולה ויורד
korban oleh ve-yored and the יולדת, yoledes, okay.
Here basically you started with a חטאת, chatas so a חטאת chatas,
is going to come first. Whereas here he's assuming an עולה olah
of a large animal comes before a חטאת. chatas So the עולה
olah is weightier. Since the עולה olah is weightier it's going to
remain weightier when you translate it into birds. Number one. Number two,
this is about sin. When it's about sin, like you got to
say you're sorry first and you got to have the חטאת chatas.
come first, that's what we sort of said. When it's not about
sin, when it's about a טהרה taharah process, the חטאת chatas can
come second. And number three, these are all, both of these are
substitute for the חטאת. chatas This number three sounds a lot like
number one. Are substitute for the חטאת, chatas. so חטאת chatas, is
the emphasis. Here they're not both substitute for a חטאת, chatas so
again עולה olah comes first. So the upshot of all of this
is that here it's actually not true what the argument that we
said. If you have a bigger עולה, olah it's actually a sheep
or whatever עולה, olah, that comes before a חטאת, chatas, and not
only that, even when it translates into two birds, the עולה olah,
is going to come first, okay, even though it's a bird עולה
olah before a bird חטאת. chatas, So quite different than we said
before. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא למקרא היא הקדימה הכתוב.
Amar Rava lemikra hi hikdima hakatuv. So רבא Rava actually says, you
know what? He didn't mean it, although it certainly sounds like he
means it. It says what he really means is is that the
פסוקים pesukim mention the עולה olah first. But he's not actually saying
that the עולה olah gets brought first. Now that's a little bit
bizarre. You're not going to a whole big explanation to say here's
why it's mentioned in the פסוק pasuk first. So תוספות Tosafos says
it doesn't just mean it's mentioned in the פסוק pasuk first, it
means if I am this woman who's just given birth, and I
have to decide which one I'm going to sanctify first, I should
first sanctify my עולה. olah Okay, so it's talking about which one
you sanctify first but not which one you bring first. Again, those
are weak answers. It sounds definitely like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer rejects
this and says when the חטאת עולה Chattas Olah are a pair
and it's about sin, the חטאת chatas. comes first. But in this
case where it's about cleansing and other types of things or whatever,
okay, and the עולה olah. is weightier, the עולה olah comes first.
That's what it sounds like, but the גמרא Gemara rejects it and
the גמרא Gemara says he's only talking about the פסוקים pesukim or
he's only talking about how you sanctify it and so on. תא
שמע, Ta shema, let's try again. פרים קודמין לאילים ואילים קודמין לכבשים
וכבשים לשעירים. Parim kodmin le'eilim ve'eilim kodmin likvasim uchvasim lise'irim. Okay, so
it all goes by the size of the animal. Cow, you know,
ram, sheep, goat, that's the order. Okay now, what type what that's
what type of animal it is, but what type of a קרבן
is it? So מאי לאו דחד? Mai lav dechad? Isn't, aren't we
talking about when you have all of these as one קרבן, you
know, cows, rams, sheep etcetera. You have it on פסח Pesach on
סוכות. Sukkos. Okay, but the what are the goats? The goats are
a חטאת. chatas So it sounds like this is the order you
bring a קרבן מוסף korban musaf on סוכות Sukkos for and it
sounds like the bigger animals come first to the smaller animal that's
a חטאת. chatas So actually, it's when you when you actually have
different types of animals, the bigger animal comes first and you don't
go חטאת chatas. עולה, olah you go by the bigger animal. Okay,
so similarly you would go by a sheep עולה olah before a
bird חטאת. chatas. מאי לאו דחד? Mai lav dechad? לא דנדבה. Lo
dindava. No, it means that you have all these different types of
עולות, olos, people are bringing עולות olos and you have to decide
which one to bring first. We're not talking about this one קרבן
מוסף korban musaf that has also a חטאת chatas in it. Now
what what is the reason for this order? פרים קודמין לאילים שכן
נתרבו בנסכים. Parim kodmin le'eilim sheken nitrabu binesachim.
Because cow before a ram because there's more in terms of the
wine and the flour and so on when you you know that
accompany it. וכן אילים לכבשים Vechen eilim likvasim and similarly rams to
sheep. כבשים לשעירים Kvasim lise'irim now why sheep come before goats if
it's the same נסכים? nesachim? שכן נתרבו באליה Sheken nitrabu be'alyah because
they have a fat tail. Now even though both of these
are what do you call
it you know are עולות olos and they're burnt up fully, okay,
whereas the bigger difference of the fat tail is when it's not
an עולה olah, that one you know one has a fat tail
that gets burnt and the other doesn't, nevertheless, okay, it's an extra
thing about it that's put on the מזבח, you know, in other
cases and therefore that's the priority. So anyway the גמרא Gemara said
here, look, this is the question. The question is which which scale
are you going to look at? Are you going to look at
size of the like you know size of the animal, like animal
versus birds versus flour, or are you going to look at חטאת
chatas. versus עולה? olah So the simple sense here is that the
larger animal comes first even if it means an עולה olah comes
for a חטאת chatas or even if it means here a you
know a cow עולה olah? comes before a bird חטאת. chatas But
the גמרא Gemara is getting out of it and saying no no
no, we're talking about not a חטאת chatas here, it's all the
same. Okay, תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here. פר קודם למשיח
קודם לפר העלם דבר של ציבור. Par kodem lemashiach kodem lefar he'elam
davar shel tzibbur. If you have the ox
of a כהן גדול kohen gadol for his sin offering comes before
the ox of
you know for the case when the בית דין beis din paskens
incorrectly. Okay, so now okay and that's because just the way the
פסוקים pesukim are written, the one of the כהן גדול kohen gadol
comes first. Now so so far that doesn't tell us anything. Those
are both a חטאת. chatas. Okay now, פר העלם דבר של ציבור
קודם לפר עבודה זרה. Par he'elam davar shel tzibbur kodem lefar avodah
zarah. The פר par for the case of the בית דין beis
din paskening incorrectly comes before the פר par of עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. Now this does tell us something because that well that's a
חטאת chatas but the פר par actually doesn't tell us anything yet.
The פר par of עבודה זרה avodah zarah is actually an עולה.
olah Okay, so okay so so far, okay fine, a חטאת chatas.
comes before an עולה, olah no big deal there. פר עבודה זרה
קודם לשעיר עבודה זרה. Par avodah zarah kodem lesair avodah zarah. Ah,
here's the kicker. Okay, the ox of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, which
is an עולה olah. comes before the goat of עבודה זרה avodah
zarah which is a חטאת. chatas So here you have it, an
עולה olah, is coming before a חטאת chatas why? Because it's a
cow coming before a goat. So here you have it just like
the question of bird versus you know bird versus sheep or whatever.
Here you it once again seems against the contention you're making that
you go by. more important animal rather than the חטאת chatas. עולה
olah priority. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says דאף
על גב דפר עבודה זרה עולה, de'af al gav de'par avoda zara
olah, even though the פר par is an עולה, olah and שעיר
עבודה זרה חטאת, se'ir avoda zara chatas, you see that the ox,
which is more important, comes before the goat. It doesn't go חטאת
chatas עולה. Olah When you have to choose between the חטאת Chatas
עולה olah, priority and the size of the animal, I mean like
the species of the animal, the animal wins out. That's what it
sounds like from all of these cases. So the גמרא Gemara says
ואימא מרישא, ve'eima me'reisha, why I don't understand says the גמרא, Gemara
why not infer the opposite from the beginning of this? פר העלם
דבר של ציבור קודם לפר עבודה זרה, Par He'elam Davar Shel Tzibur
kodem le'par avoda zara, that a חטאת Chatas of the בית דין
Beis Din comes before the עולה Olah. of עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, of course if they're the same
type of animal, בחד מינא מי לא קאמרינן דחטאת
קדמה, be'chad mina mi lo ka'amrinan de'chatas kadma, the גמרא Gemara says
I'm not challenging the basic argument. Of course I agree in general
a חטאת Chatas comes first. Nobody's challenging that, that a חטאת Chatas
comes first. But that's when the types of animals are the same.
So if you have to choose between a bird חטאת Chatas and
a bird עולה, Olah you're going to go a bird חטאת Chatas
first. If you have to choose between a cow חטאת Chatas and
a cow עולה, Olah you're going to do a cow חטאת Chatas
first. So of course, hey buddy, nobody is challenging the idea that
a חטאת Chatas comes before an עולה. Olah, So okay, that's generally
true. What we're asking is when the עולה Olah, is of a
different, of a like a bigger species of animal. That's when we
want to say that an עולה Olah. comes first, okay, that a
sheep עולה Olah comes before a bird חטאת, Chatas that a cow
עולה Olah comes before a goat חטאת. Chatas Okay, that's what we're
trying to prove and it seems like we've proved it. כי קאמרינן
בתרי מיני, ki ka'amrinan bi'trei minei, okay, with two different types of
animals. אשכחן עולה דקדמה לחטאת, ashkchan olah de'kadma le'chatas, so you see
here a cow עולה Olah by עבודה זרה Avoda Zara comes before
the goat חטאת. Chatas, So look at this, lookie here, an עולה
Olah comes before a חטאת. Chatas. Okay, so אמרי במערבא, amri be'ma'arava,
so that seems to be a pretty darn good proof. Pretty much
everything they've said seems to be a pretty good proof that when
you're choosing within the animals, okay, that the species of animal is
the bigger weight. So the גמרא Gemara says אמרי במערבא בארץ ישראל
amri be'ma'arava be'Eretz Yisrael they say, okay, you're right, but here's why.
משמיה דרבא בר מרי חטאת עבודה זרה חסר אלף לחטאת כתיב. mi'shmei
de'Rava bar Mari chatas avoda zara chaser aleph le'chatas ksiv. In general
no, we still hold by our position. You go by חטאת Chatas.
comes before an עולה Olah even if they're different species of animals,
okay? So why by עבודה זרה Avoda Zara does the עולה Olah
come first? Okay, טאקע, taka, why by עבודה זרה Avoda Zara does
the עולה Olah come first? Because the word חטאת Chatas. by עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara is spelled without an אלף, aleph, which is a
demoting of its status, okay? So normally in all other cases I
don't care, cow, sheep, bird, חטאת Chatas always comes before an עולה.
Olah It doesn't matter the species of the animal, okay? The one
exception is עבודה זרה Avoda Zara because it's missing an אלף aleph
and that says that a חטאת Chatas comes second. רבינא אמר כמשפט
כתיב בהו, Ravina amar ke'mishpat ksiv be'hu, or here's another reason, it
says by the עבודה זרה Avoda Zara כמשפט. ke'mishpat. So since in
by עבודה זרה Avoda Zara it mentions עולה Olah first and it
says you do it like we're like you're being told, it's a
special הלכה halacha by the by the עבודה זרה Avoda Zara קרבן
that an עולה Olah. comes first, okay? But as a general rule,
חטאת Chatas always comes first even a bird חטאת Chatas comes before
a cow עולה. Olah Okay, that's the rule. Now the גמרא Gemara
says השתא דאתית להכי, hashta de'asis le'hachi, now that we're allowing for
the fact that there could be some exceptions, you know what else
I'll say, I'll get rid of another proof you had from before
and I'll say that אפילו תימא פרים דחג, afilu teima parim de'chag,
you know what the proof you had before about the cows and
the goats and the sheep and the whole thing, okay, and you
thought that it was talking about the מוסף mussaf of סוכות? Succos?
I'll concede the point and I'll say that in the מוסף mussaf
of סוכות, Succos, you're right, the עולות olos come before the חטאת.
Chatas But that's not a general rule, it's an exception, and the
reason that happens there is כי כמשפטם כתיב בהו, ki ke'mishpatam ksiv
be'hu, because the way the תורה Torah lists it, if you just
think about how you say the מוסף mussaf in שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh
Esrei, right, you always mention all of the עולות olos and then
you say ושעיר עזים אחד לחטאת, ve'se'ir izim echad le'chatas, right, you
throw in the חטאת Chatas at the end. Right? So the גמרא's
Gemara saying you know what, maybe you're right by a מוסף, mussaf,
maybe because there the תורה Torah says כמשפט. ke'mishpat. So basically what
we're saying is there's pretty good evidence that when it's a bigger
species of animal that takes priority over חטאת Chatas. and עולה. Olah
But the גמרא's Gemara rejecting that and the גמרא says no the
rule is חטאת Chatas always comes first, even a bird חטאת Chatas
comes before a cow עולה, Olah. okay? That's the rule. There are
some admittedly there are and again even though it seems like רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that certainly not true here by the יולדת, yoledes,
okay, the גמרא sort of got rid of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and it said there are some exceptions though when the תורה Torah
explicitly within one קרבן gives the priority in a different way and
says כמשפט. ke'mishpat. So where would that be? By עבודה זרה Avoda
Zara it says that the that the עולה Olah. comes before the
חטאת, Chatas that's true, okay, the cow עולה Olah, comes before the
goat חטאת. Chatas and by מוסף, Mussaf, the חטאת Chatas, comes at
the end. So it is true, there are some exceptions when it's
explicit. But bracketing those exceptions, חטאת Chatas. always comes first, even a
lower species of animal. Okay, let's finish up to the משנה. איבעיא
להו: Ibayya lehu: they raised the following question: חטאת העוף ועולת בהמה
ומעשר איזה מהן קודם? Chattas ha-Of ve-Olat Behemah u-Maaser eizeh me-hen kodem?
So you have a bird חטאת, Chattas a sheep עולה, Olah which
now we've said that the bird חטאת Chattas comes first, okay, and
you have מעשר. Maaser Which comes first? Okay, איזה מהן קודם? eizeh
me-hen kodem?
תיקדום חטאת העוף. Tikdom Chattas ha-Of. Logically חטאת העוף Chattas ha-Of should
come, right? Because if you think about it,
okay, you've got—so now we've decided that חטאת העוף Chattas ha-Of and
עולת בהמה, Olat Behemah,
this is always number one and this is always number two. Okay.
Now we've got מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah. and we've said that when
it's between מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah, and עולה, Olah okay, when you're
looking at the comparison here, okay, this is an עולה, Olah, this
is קדשי קדשים, this is קדשים קלים. This is number one and
this is number two. Okay. Now logically you would think that if
this is weightier than this, חטאת Chattas, is weightier than an עולה,
Olah, then the חטאת Chattas should be weightier than מעשר בהמה. Maaser
Behemah And it should be obvious, one, two, three, right? That should
be obvious. But for some bizarre reason the גמרא is saying that
logically we do understand that bigger animals are more important. So this
idea that a bird comes before a בהמה behemah by חטאת העוף
Chattas ha-Of is only something we know about a חטאת העוף. Chattas
ha-Of. If you had to choose between—the גמרא sounds like, forget the
עולה Olah, was in the picture—ראובן Reuven brought a חטאת העוף Chattas
ha-Of and שמעון Shimon brought מעשר בהמה. Maaser Behemah, So now logically
you would say if a חטאת העוף Chattas ha-Of comes before an
עולת בהמה, Olat Behemah, an עולה Olah, which is weightier, certainly a
חטאת Chattas should come before like a שלמים, Shelamim right? Logically you'd
do the חטאת Chattas first. But the גמרא is not prepared to
say that. We only know this about a חטאת העוף. Chattas ha-Of.
And maybe if it were between these two, a חטאת העוף Chattas
ha-Of and a מעשר בהמה, Maaser Behemah maybe you would bring the
שלמים Shelamim first because it's a bigger animal. Okay? So if that's
true, if it's between these two, this could come first. This is
only a הלכה halakhah of חטאת Chattas and עולה. Olah Then you're
never going to figure out which one is going to come first.
Okay?
So the גמרא says like this:
so תיקדום חטאת העוף, tikdom Chattas ha-Of, let a חטאת העוף Chattas
ha-Of come first. איכא מעשר דקדים ליה. ika Maaser de-kadim leh. So
no, מעשר should come first because this is a בהמה behemah and
this comes before חטאת Chattas even though it's only a שלמים Shelamim
since it's not this special הלכה halakhah of חטאת העוף. Chattas ha-Of.
So you can't say this, one, two, three which is logical, because
מעשר should come before חטאת. Chattas Okay? ליקדום מעשר, Likdom Maaser, let
מעשר come first. איכא עולת בהמה דקדמה ליה. ika Olat Behemah de-kadmah
leh. No, because then you're having מעשר coming before an עולה, Olah
and obviously this is like a שלמים shelamim, and this is an
עולה, Olah. and an עולה Olah, should come first. Okay? תיקדום עולת
בהמה, Tikdom Olat Behemah, let the עולה Olah, come first. No, איכא
חטאת העוף דקדמה לה. ika Chattas ha-Of de-kadmah lah. When it's—when it's
between an עולה Olah and a חטאת, Chattas an עולה, Olah then
the חטאת Chattas. has to come first. So which way are you
going to choose? So הכא תרגימו, hacha targinu, sort of like, you
know, what is it—who was it?
Occam's—who was it, like the goat that—the animal, you know, if you
put two piles of hay that are exactly the same, you know,
like some philosopher said that like animals can't make arbitrary choices. So
if you put two piles of hay in front of it that
are exactly the same in terms of appearance and smell and distance
or whatever, the animal would just like die of starvation because it
couldn't make an arbitrary choice. Anyway, so we'll never be able to
leave the בית המקדש because we can't figure out—what now? Of course
not true. Anyway, so the גמרא says okay. דקדמה ליה, De-kadmah leh,
so the גמרא says הכא תרגימו—מן זבח. Here in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael we say that at the end of the day, okay, מעשר
comes first because it is ultimately a—more—זבח, meaning it's like slaughtered as
opposed to the עולה. Olah So while we are not allowed to
preference the larger animal here, the בהמה behemah to the bird between
a חטאת Chattas, and an עולה, Olah, but we are going to
basically let the מעשר בהמה maaser behema. come first, okay? And so
it's going to be מעשר בהמה, maaser behema. this has to come
as a package, as a חטאת Chattas עולה Olah. package. עולה Olah,
has to come second, okay, and then we're going to have the
מעשר בהמה come
first. Okay? מן זבח עדיף. Min zevach adif. במערבא אמרי, Be-ma'arava amri,
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they say, איידי דבאה עולת בהמה בחטאת
העוף ואגבה ממעשר. aydi de-ba-ah Olat Behemah be-Chattas ha-Of ve-agbah mi-Maaser. No,
because this comes as a package, the חטאת Chattas עולה Olah package
means that all of this takes precedence over the מעשר. Because this
has—why would you want מעשר to take precedence? Because it's a larger
animal over a חטאת העוף. Chattas ha-Of. But because this is a
package, this package חטאת chatas עולה Olah. has a larger animal in
it. So this package is going to come first, okay, which obviously
makes sense, but again רש"י seems to imply that not only does
this come first because it's a package, but also once you're saying
this logically we should say if a bird עולה. olah. A bird
חטאת chatas comes before an עולת בהמה, olas behema, a bird, a
bird חטאת chatas should also come before מעשר בהמה. But in the
end it seems like the גמרא is saying that, it's saying we
only know that priority between חטאת chatas and עולה. We would actually
choose otherwise if it was חטאת and שלמים, but because this is
a package, that's going to come before the מעשר בהמה. So there's
a debate which way to go for that. Okay, we will continue
with the משנה tomorrow.